# STEPHEN GIFT MUKOYA ARAKA

@: stevenaraka@gmail.com

**\**: (+250) 784 014 210

(iii): LinkedIn | Github | Portfolio

#### **CAREER SUMMARY**

Computer scientist with three years of extensive experience in software development. Designs, creates, and maintains software products for companies and to enhance business operations. Contributed as a front-end engineer in building a cloud-native tool to save locally based African developers over 40% in bandwidth usage for deploying applications. Seeking an opportunity to apply skills and expand expertise in Software and DevOps engineering while assisting companies to meet business goals and be future proof.

#### **EDUCATION**

## Carnegie Mellon University – Africa, Rwanda

Aug 2020 – expected Dec 2022

Master of Science in Information Technology

CGPA 3.35

Department of Information and Communication Technology

# Makerere University - Uganda

Aug 2016 – May 2019

Bachelor of Science Computer Science

CGPA 3.92

College of Computing and Information Science

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

## **Graduate Teaching Assistant – Software Architecture and Design**

Jan 2022 - Present

Carnegie Mellon University, Africa - Rwanda

- Currently coordinating a class of 14 students to develop skills in designing, developing, and justifying reasonable software architecture for enterprise-scale software-intensive systems, considering both functional and nonfunctional requirements as well as contextual system environments.
- Organizing recitations, assignments, and discussions to accord students a smooth transition in Software Architecture and Design.

## **Graduate Teaching Assistant – First Year Seminar**

Aug 2021 - Dec 2021

Carnegie Mellon University, Africa – Rwanda

Assisted a class of 48 students in developing students' career skills and broadening professional horizons through
exposure to a wide-ranging set of issues in ICT.

## **DevOps Engineer – Intern**

Jun 2021 – Sep 2021

Crane Cloud - Uganda

- Analysed current containerization processes used by Crane Cloud users.
- Researched on containerization best practices drawn from industry.
- Implemented and tested initial version of a Docker containerization pipeline for over 200 users.

## **Software Engineer**

Apr 2019 – Dec 2020

Crane Cloud - Uganda

• Designed and implemented <u>cranecloud.io</u>, a web platform used to manage Infrastructure-as-a Service on premise and multiple public clouds while working specifically as a leading front-end engineer.

• Optimized product for a fitting user experience and launched <u>cranecloud.io</u> through a webinar to accelerate adoption of cloud native solutions in Uganda and Africa at large.

Software Developer Nov 2019 – Jan 2020

REF. Sports Limited - Uganda

• Cemented company's online presence through designing and building an e-commerce website.

Software Developer Jan 2019 – Mar 2019

Line23 - Uganda

• Executed the implementation of a mobile application to aid team collaboration.

## **Developer Consultant - Intern**

Jun 2018 – Sep 2018

Flock of Birds - Uganda

- Developed widgets for Mendix, a low-code software platform to build, test, deploy and iterate applications, by working with fellow interns.
- Gained hands-on experience in software development and consultancy through engaging and helping customers with questions about company products and services.
- Selected among 8 interns and retained to work as permanent staff.

## **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Frontend: React, Next.js, JavaScript (ES6), TypeScript, Bootstrap, HTML, CSS, Sass, UI Design (Figma).

Backend: Node.js, Express.js, Web Sockets (socket.io), MySQL, MongoDB, PostgreSQL.

**DevOps:** Docker, Heroku, CI/CD (CircleCI, Jenkins), Cloud Computing (AWS, GCP, Azure), Kubernetes, Terraform, Helm, Ansible, Vagrant.

**Project Management & Collaboration:** Version Control (Git), Jira, Trello, Pivotal Tracker, Agile Software Development (Scrum & Kanban).

#### **PROJECTS**

- Estimation of carbon emission reduction from forestry for carbon credits trading [Jan 2022 Present].
- High performance Twitter Analytics Web Service on the cloud (Terraform, Kubernetes, Helm, AWS, GCP, Azure, Microservices) [Sep 2021 Dec 2021].

## **HONORS AND AWARDS**

- Recognized for volunteering as a Mastercard Foundation facilitator for a bootcamp to teach programming basics to students using Python (2021).
- Recipient of a full scholarship from the Mastercard Foundation for the master's program at Carnegie Mellon University Africa (2020).
- Recognized for volunteering as an organizer for the Bright Summer School at Makerere University to enhance ICT Training and Research in Uganda (2017).